(Transcribed by TurboScribe.ai. Go Unlimited to remove this message.) All right, welcome back to 006 Data Structures
اليوم سنتناول نوعًا مختلفًا
من بنية بيانات تشبه الشجرة وتسمى "هيب"
الهيب الثنائي
سيمكننا هذا من حل مشكلات الفرز
بطريقة جديدة
دعوني أذكّركم أولًا بجزء معين
المشكلة التي سنحلها اليوم
تُسمى "طابور الأولويات"
هذه هي الواجهة
We'll see several data structures, but one main
data structure for today
And this is a subset of the set
interface
And subsets are interesting because potentially we can
solve them better, faster, simpler, something
And so you'll recognize, you should recognize all
of these operations, except we didn't normally highlight
the max operation
So here we're interested in storing a bunch
of items
They have keys, which we think of as
priorities
And we want to be able to identify
the maximum priority item in our set and
remove it
And so there's lots of motivations for this
Maybe you have a router, packets going into
the router, they have different priorities assigned to
them, you want to route the highest priority
first
Or you have processes on your computer trying
to run on your single-threaded, single core,
and you've got to choose which one to
run next, and you usually run higher priority
processes first
Or you're trying to simulate a system where
events happen at different times, and you want
to process the next event ordered by time
All of these are examples of the priority
queue interface
We'll even see applications within this class when
we get to graph algorithms
But the main two things we want to
be able to support are inserting an item,
which includes a key, and deleting the maximum
item, and also returning it at the same
time
We'll also talk some about being able to
build the structure faster than just inserting it
But of course we could implement build by
starting empty and repeatedly inserting
And also the complexity of just finding the
max without deleting it
This you could simulate with these two operations
by deleting the max and then reinserting it
Which works
But often we can do faster
But the two key main operations are insert
and delete max
And we're going to see a few data
structures to do this
Any suggestions among the data structures we've seen
in this class?
What should we use to solve priority queue
interface?
Many possible answers
Sequence AVL
Oh, that's interesting
Sequence AVL is a good answer
But it's maybe the fancier version
Yeah
Set AVL
Sounds good
Set AVL supports these operations and many more
All in log n time, except for build,
which takes n log n time
Because you have to sort first
So set AVL is a good way to
do this
We'll come back to your sequence AVL idea
later
This gets log n for operation
Great
I mean, set AVL is our most powerful
data structure
It does all the operations we care about
On the set side
And the sequence AVL does all the operations
on the sequence side
But note that this is a set, not
a sequence
We care about keys
There are hacks to get around that with
sequence AVLs
But let's do that later
So great
If we wanted to, for example, speed up
find max in a set AVL, we could
add augmentation
We could remember subtree property augmentations
We can use that to get constant time
find max by storing in every node the
maximum key item within the subtree
And that's a subtree property
It's one we mentioned last class
So we could even improve that to constant
time
Great
So we're done
End of lecture
In some sense, that's true
But what we're going to see today is
another data structure called a binary heap, which
is, in some sense, a simplification of set
AVL
It achieves basically the same time bounds
Build will be faster by a log factor
But that's not the main reason we care
about them
The main advantage is that they're simpler
And they give us an in-place sorting
algorithm
So I have up here the three of
the operations I've been talking about, build, insert,
and delete max
So we have set AVL, trees there, n
log n build, log n insert, log n
delete
So along the way to our heap, I
want to mention two other data structures
One is a dynamic but unsorted array
And the other is a dynamic sorted array
These are simpler data structures we've talked about
many times before
And they're useful motivations for getting started
Because a heap is going to be built
on top of arrays instead of a fusion
between arrays and trees
So if I have an unsorted array, this
is very easy to insert into
I just append to the end
This is what we called insert last
So insert is fast, constant amortized
We might have to resize the array
So that's the amortized part
But delete max is slow in an unsorted
array
I don't know where the maximum is
So I have to scan through the whole
array
So I scan through the array, identify the
max is somewhere in the middle
And then if I want to delete it,
I want to delete that maximum element
Well, in a dynamic array, all I can
really do is delete the last element efficiently
So I could, for example, swap it with
the last element
So I take this element and put it
here, and then delete the last element in
that array, which is pop in Python, or
delete last in our world
So overall, this is linear time, which is
bad
But I wanted to highlight exactly how it's
done for a reason we'll get to in
a moment
Sorted array is sort of the reverse
It's very easy to find the max
Where is it?
At the end
Delete max
The maximum element is always the last element
in a increasing sorted array
I guess that's constant amortized, because then I
have to delete it, which may incur resizing
Insert, though, is going to be linear, because
maybe I can binary search to find where
the added item belongs
Let's say I just added this item here
I could binary search to find it, but
then I'm going to have to do a
big shift
So I might as well just swap repeatedly
until I find the position where the added
item x belongs
And now I've restored sorted order
That takes linear time, which is bad
And what we want is somehow the best
of these two worlds
Insert is fast for array
Delete is fast for a sorted array
We can't get constant time for both, but
we can get log n time for both
We already know how with set AVL trees
But we're going to see a different way
to do it today
And the main motivation for a different way
to do this is sorting
So I want to define priority queue sort
So given any data structure that implements a
priority queue interface, in particular, insert and delete
max, I can make a sorting algorithm
What do I do?
Insert all the items, delete all the items
But because when I delete them, they come
out largest first, I get them in reverse
sorted order
Then I could reverse in linear time, and
I've sorted my items
So we can insert x for x and
a, or build a, and then repeatedly
delete max
How much time does this algorithm take?
I'm going to introduce some notation here
It takes however long it takes to build
n items
I'll call that t sub build of n
plus n times the
time to do a delete max
Or we can write this as n times
time to do an insert plus time to
do a delete max
So I'm using these t functions to just
abstract what are the running times provided by
my data structure that implements this interface
Interface says what's correct is, and these t
functions give me my performance bounds
So if I plug in each of these
data structures, I get a sorting algorithm
I get AVL sort
I get array sort
I get assorted array sort
What do those look like?
It turns out many of these are familiar
So set AVLs take log n per operation
So we get an n log n sorting
algorithm out of them, which is insert all
of the items into the AVL tree
I don't want to use AVL build because
that uses sort
I'm not allowed to sort in order to
implement sort
But we saw how to insert into an
AVL tree and keep the thing balanced
So that takes log n each
And then we can find the max, delete
it, rebalance, and so on
Total time will be n log n
This is an algorithm we call AVL sort
It's a bit complicated because AVL trees are
complicated
But it gives us optimal comparison bound, n
log n
Now, what about array sort?
So suppose I use an unsorted array
I insert the item
So if I insert the items, so I'm
doing all the insertions here before all the
deletions
So what's going to happen is I just
insert the items in the original array order
In other words, I just take the array
And then what I do is repeatedly extract
the maximum item by searching for it, moving
it to the end of the array, and
then repeating that process
That sound familiar?
That's selection sort from lecture three
So this arrays give us selection sort
This is a new way to think about
what we were doing way back then
With a sorted array, what are we doing?
We insert all the items
That's actually where all the work happens because
we maintain the sorted array
So we start with an empty array
It's sorted
We add an item
OK, still sorted
We add a second item
And we swap if we need to in
order to sort
In general, when we add an item, we
swap it to the left until it's sorted
again
That is insertion sort
Kind of cool
This is a unifying framework for three sorting
algorithms that we saw before
We didn't actually talk about AVL sort last
time, but it was in the notes
And so that is the right part of
this table
So of course, these array data structures are
not efficient
They take linear time for some of the
operations, so the sorting algorithms are not efficient
But they're ones we've seen before, so it's
neat to see how they fit in here
They had the selection sort and insertion sort
had the advantage that they were in place
You just needed a constant number of pointers
or indices beyond the array itself
So they're very space efficient
So that was a plus for them
But they take n squared time, so you
should never use them
Except for n at most 100 or something
AVL tree sort is great in that it
gets n log n time
Probably more complicated than merge sort, and you
could stick to merge sort
But neither merge sort nor set AVL tree
sort are in place
And so the goal of today is to
get the best of all those worlds in
sorting to get n log n comparisons, which
is optimal in the comparison model, but get
it to be in place
And that's what we're going to get with
binary heaps
We're going to design a data structure that
happens to build a little bit faster, as
I mentioned, linear time building
So it's not representing a sorted order in
the same way that AVL trees are
But it will be kind of tree based
It will also be array based
We're going to get logarithmic time for insert
and delete max
This happens to be amortized because we use
arrays
But the key thing is that it's an
in-place data structure
It only consists of an array of the
items
And so when we plug it into our
sorting algorithm, priority queue sort, our generic sorting
algorithm, not only do we get n log
n performance, but we also get an in
-place sorting algorithm
This will be our first and only in
this class, n log n in-place sorting
algorithm
Cool
That's the goal
Let's do it
So what we're going to do, because we're
in place, basically we have to have an
array storing our n items
That's sort of the definition of in-place,
just using n slots of memory, exactly the
size of the number of items in our
structure
But we're obviously not going to use a
regular unsorted array or a regular sorted array
We're going to use array just as sort
of the underlying technology for how things are
stored
But we'd really like logarithmic performance, which should
make you think tree
Only way to get a log is with
the binary tree, more or less
So tree
Somehow, we want to embed a tree into
an array
Let me grab an example
Let me draw a tree
If I got to choose any old tree
I want, I would choose a tree that's
basically perfectly balanced
Perfectly balanced would be like this, where what's
the property?
That I have all of these levels, all
of these depths are completely filled with nodes
This is depth 0
Remember, this is depth 1
This is depth 2
This is depth 3
So what I'd really like is to have
2 to the i nodes at depth i
That would be a perfect binary tree
But that only works when n is 1
less than a power of 2
I can't always achieve that for any n
And so the next best thing I could
hope for is 2 to the i nodes
at depth i until the very last i,
the largest depth
And in that level, I'm still going to
restrict things
I'm going to force all of the nodes
to be as far left as possible
So I want to say, except at max
depth, where nodes are, I'll
call them, left justified
And these two properties together is what I
call a complete binary tree
Why is this interesting?
Because I claim I can represent a tree
like this as an array
I've narrowed things down enough that I can
draw an array down here
And what I'm going to do is write
these nodes in depth order
So I'll write a first, because that's depth
Then bc, that's depth 1
Then, well, they're alphabetical
I made it that way
defg is depth 2
And then hij is depth 3
This is very different from traversal order of
a tree
Traversal order would have been h, d, i,
b, j, e, a, f, c, g
OK, but this is what we might call
depth order
Do the lowest depth nodes first
Very different way to lay things out or
to linearize our data
And this is what a heap is going
to look like
So the cool thing is, between complete binary
trees and arrays is a bijection
For every array, there's a unique complete binary
tree
And for every complete binary tree, there's a
unique array
Why?
Because the complete constraint forces everything, forces my
hand
There's only, if I give you a number
n, there is one tree shape of size
n
You just fill in the nodes, top down,
until you get to the last level
And then you have to fill them in
left to right, what you might call reading
order for writing down nodes
And the array is telling you which keys
go where
This is the first node you write down
at the root
This is the next node you write down
at the left child of the root, and
so on
So here we have a binary tree represented
as an array, or an array representing a
binary tree
The very specific binary tree, it has a
clear advantage, which is it is guaranteed balanced
No rotation is necessary in heaps, because complete
binary trees are always balanced
In fact, they have the best height they
possibly could, which is ceiling of log n
Balanced, remember, just meant you were big O
of log n
This is 1 times log n
So it's the best level of balance you
could hope for
So somehow, I claim, we can maintain a
complete binary tree for solving priority queues
This would not be possible if you were
trying to solve the whole set interface
And that's kind of the cool thing about
heaps, is that by just focusing on the
subset of the set interface, we can do
more
We can maintain this very strong property
And because we have this very strong property,
we don't even need to store this tree
We're not going to store left and right
pointers and parent pointers
We're just going to store the array
This is what we call an implicit data
structure, which
basically means no pointers, just an array of
the n items
How are we going to get away without
storing pointers?
I'd still like to treat it like a
tree
I'd still like to know the left child
of B is D and the right child
of B is E
We'll see why in a moment
Well, we can do this with index arithmetic
So maybe I should add some labels before
I get there
So this array naturally has indices
This is index 0
This is index 1, index 2, index 3,
index 4, index 5, index 6, 7, 8,
9, because there are 10 items, 0 through
And I can apply those labels up here,
too
These are the same nodes
So 0, 1, 2
This is just depth order
But once I have this labeling, it's going
to be a lot easier to figure things
out
So if I wanted to know the left
child of B is D, somehow, given the
number 1, I want to compute the number
3, add 2, multiply by 3
There are all sorts of operations that take
1 and turn it into 3
But there's only one that's going to work
in all cases
And the intuition here is, well, I have
2 to the i nodes at level i
If I want to go to the child
level, there's 2 to the i plus 1
nodes down there, exactly double
Except the very last one, but that won't
really matter
If there is a left child, it will
behave the same
And so intuitively, I have this space of
size 2 to the i
I have to expand it to a space
of size 2 to the i plus 1
So I should multiply by 2
And that's almost right
But then there's some constants
So I'd like to say 2 times i
But if we look at the examples here,
1 times 2 is 2, which is 1
less than 3
2 times 2 is 4, which is 1
less than 5
Hey, we almost got it right
It's just off by 1
1 is index errors are the most common
things in computer science
What about the right child?
If the left child is a 2i plus
1, where's the right child?
I hear lots of mumbles
2i plus 2
One more
Because we're writing things left to right in
depth order, the right child is the right
sibling of the left child
So it's just one larger
Given those rules, we can also compute parent
It's just whatever is the inverse of both
of these functions, which I want to divide
by 2 at some point
But I want to get back to i
given 2i plus 1 or given 2i plus
And so if I subtract 1 from i,
then I either get 2i or 2i plus
And then if I take an integer division
by 2, I get i, the original i
Sorry, maybe I'll call this j to be
clearer
So j is the left or right child
Then I can reconstruct i, which was the
parent
So this is a constant number arithmetic operation
So I don't have to store left and
right pointers
I can just compute them whenever I need
them
Whenever I'm at some node like E, and
I want to know what's its left child,
sorry, given the node index 4, which happens
to contain the item E, and I want
to know what's its left child, I just
multiply by 2 and add 1
I get 9
Then I can index into this array at
position 9, because this is just in my
head
Remember, we're just thinking that there's a tree
here
But in reality, on the computer, there's just
the array
So if we want to go from E
to j, we can, from 4 to 9
If we try to go to the right
child, we multiply by 2, 8, add 2,
And we see, oh, 10 is beyond the
end of the array
But our array stores its size
So we realize, oh, E does not have
a right child
This is something you can only do in
a complete binary tree
In a general binary tree, you don't have
these nice properties
Cool
So this is basically a heap
I just need to add one more property,
naturally, called the heap property
So there are multiple types of heaps
This type of heap is called a binary
heap
We will talk about others in future lectures
I'm going to call it Q
Maybe I should write the explicit
thing
This is an array representing a complete binary
tree called the
array Q
And we want every node to satisfy
the so-called max heap property, which
says Q of i is greater than or
equal to Q of j for both children
left of i and right of i
So we have a node, i, and has
two children, 2i plus 1 and 2i plus
These are our two values of j
What we want is a greater than or
equal to relation here and here
So this node should be bigger than both
this one and this one
Which of these is larger?
We don't know
And we don't care
Very different from binary search trees or set
binary trees, where we said these guys were
less than or equal to this one
This one was less than or equal to
all the nodes in the subtree
Here, we're just locally saying this node is
greater than or equal to this node and
this node
So the biggest is at the top
So one nice lemma about these heaps, this
is weird
Let me give you some more intuition
If you are a binary heap, if you
satisfy this max heap property everywhere, then, in
fact, you learn that every node i is
greater than or equal to all nodes in
its subtree
These are what we call descendants and subtree
of i
Let me look at this example
So I haven't written any numbers here, but
you can imagine
So a here is greater than or equal
to both b and c
And b is greater than or equal to
d and e
And c is greater than or equal to
f and g
And d is greater than or equal to
h and i
And e is greater than or equal to
j
That would make this structure a heap, not
just a complete binary tree
So what does that imply?
It implies that a must be the maximum
So you look at any node here, like
j, a is greater than or equal to
b, is greater than or equal to e,
is greater than or equal to j
And in general, what we're saying is that
a is greater than or equal to all
nodes in the tree
b is greater than or equal to all
nodes in its subtree, down here
c is greater than or equal to all
nodes in its subtree
That's what this lemma is saying
You can prove this lemma by induction
But it's really simple
If you have two nodes, i and j,
and j is somewhere in the subtree, that
means there's some downward path from i to
j
And you know that for every edge we
traverse on a downward path, our key is
going down non-strictly
Every child is less than or equal to
its parent
i is greater than or equal to this,
is greater than or equal to this, is
greater than or equal to this, is greater
than or equal to j
So by transitivity of less than or equal
to, you know that i is, in fact,
greater than or equal to j
Or sorry, the key in i is greater
than or equal to the key in j
This is what we're calling i, the index
This is what we would call q of
i
This is index j, q of j
OK
Very different way to organize keys in a
tree
But as you might imagine, this is going
to be good for priority queues, because priority
queues just need to find the maximum element
Then they need to delete it
That's going to be harder, because deleting the
root is like, that's the hardest node